Francesca Fedeli: Ciao.
فرانسيسكا فيديلي: مرحباً
So he's Mario. He's our son.
هاهو ماريو. ابننا
He was born two and a half years ago,
لقد وُلد قبل عامين ونصف
and I had a pretty tough pregnancy
وقد مررت بفترة حمل صعبة
because I had to stay still in a bed for, like, eight months.
لأنه توجب علي البقاء على الفراش لحوالي 8 اشهر.
But in the end everything seemed to be under control.
لكن في النهاية بدا كل شيء بخير
So he got the right weight at birth.
وقد كان وزنه مناسبا حين ميلاده.
He got the right Apgar index.
كان لديه حرز ابغار المناسب.
So we were pretty reassured by this.
لذا فقد كنا متأكدين من هذا.
But at the end, 10 days later after he was born,
لكن بعد 10 أيام من ولادته،
we discovered that he had a stroke.
أكتشفنا بأنه اصيب بسكتة دماغية.
As you might know,
ربما تعرفون،
a stroke is a brain injury.
السكتة الدماغية هي إصابة في الدماغ.
A perinatal stroke could be something
والسكتة الدماغية قبل الولادة يمكن أن يكون شيئا
that can happen during the nine months of pregnancy
قد حدث خلال الشهر التاسع للحمل
or just suddenly after the birth,
أو مباشرة بعد الميلاد،
and in his case, as you can see,
وفي حالته، كما ترون،
the right part of his brain has gone.
قد عطب الجزء الأيمن من دماغه.
So the effect that this stroke could have on Mario's body
لذا فالتأثير لهذه السكتة الدماغية على جسم ماريو
could be the fact that he couldn't be able to control
قد يكون أنه لم يعد يستطع التحكم
the left side of his body.
في الجزء الأيسر من جسمه.
Just imagine, if you have a computer and a printer
فقط تخيلوا، اذا كان لديك حاسوب و طابعة
and you want to transmit, to input to print out a document,
وأردت الارسال، أن تصدر أمرا بطباعة مستندا،
but the printer doesn't have the right drives,
لكن الطابعة لا تملك التعريف المناسب،
so the same is for Mario.
نفس هذا الأمر بالنسبة لماريو.
It's just like, he would like to move his left side
الأمر مثل، أنه يريد تحريك الجزء الأيسر
of his body, but he's not able to transmit the right input
لجسمه، لكنه لا يستطيع تمرير الأمر المناسب
to move his left arm and left leg.
لتحريك يده اليسرى ورجله اليسرى.
So life had to change.
لذا توجب علينا تغيير حياتنا.
We needed to change our schedule.
ينبغي علينا تغيير جدول أعمالنا.
We needed to change the impact that this birth had
أردنا تغيير التأثير الذي أحدثه هذا المولود
on our life.
على حياتنا.
Roberto D'Angelo: As you may imagine,
روبرتو دي أنجلو: كما تتخيلون،
unfortunately, we were not ready.
لسوء الحظ، لم نكن مستعدين.
Nobody taught us how to deal with such kinds of disabilities,
لم يعلمنا أحد كيفية التعامل مع مثل هذه الإعاقات،
and as many questions as possible started
وبدأت الكثير من الأسئلة
to come to our minds.
تخطر على بالنا.
And that has been really a tough time.
وقد كان هذا بالفعل وقتاً عصيباً.
Questions, some basics, like, you know,
أسئلة، بعضها أساسية مثل:
why did this happen to us?
لماذا حدث لنا هذا؟
And what went wrong?
و مالذي حدث بصورة خاطئة؟
Some more tough, like, really,
وبعضها بالفعل قاسية، مثل
what will be the impact on Mario's life?
ماذا سيكون التأثير على حياة ماريو؟
I mean, at the end, will he be able to work?
أعني، في النهاية، هل سيقدر على العمل؟
Will he be able to be normal?
هل سيكون فتى عادي؟
And, you know, as a parent, especially for the first time,
وكما تعلمون، كآباء، خصوصاً لأول مرة،
why is he not going to be better than us?
لماذا لن يقدر على أن يكون أفضل منا؟
And this, indeed, really is tough to say,
وهذا بالطبع، شيئ صعب قوله،
but a few months later, we realized that
لكن بعد عدة أشهر، أدركنا أننا
we were really feeling like a failure.
كنا نشعر بأنه فشل حقيقي.
I mean, the only real product of our life,
أعني، أن المنتج الوحيد الحقيقي لحياتنا،
at the end, was a failure.
في النهاية، كان فشلاً.
And you know, it was not a failure for ourselves in itself,
وكما تعلمون، لم يكن فشلاً لنا بحد ذاته،
but it was a failure that will impact his full life.
بل كان فشلاً سيؤثر على حياته بصورة كلية.
Honestly, we went down.
بكل صراحة، كُنا محبطين.
I mean we went really down, but at the end,
أعني ، كنا محبطين حقاً، لكن في النهاية،
we started to look at him,
بدأنا ننظر اليه،
and we said, we have to react.
وقلنا، ينبغي أن نفعل شيئاً.
So immediately, as Francesca said, we changed our life.
وفي الحال، كما قالت فرانسيسكا، قمنا بتغيير حياتنا.
We started physiotherapy, we started the rehabilitation,
بدأنا بالعلاج الطبيعي، وبدأنا إعادة التأهيل،
and one of the paths that we were following
وأحدى الطرق التي سلكناها
in terms of rehabilitation is the mirror neurons pilot.
من ناحية إعادة التأهيل هي مرآة الخلايا العصبية التجريبية.
Basically, we spent months doing this with Mario.
في الأساس، قضينا شهوراً نفعل هذا لماريو.
You have an object, and we showed him
يكون لديك شيء، ونريه
how to grab the object.
كيفية امساك الشيء.
Now, the theory of mirror neurons simply says
الآن، تقول نظرية مرآة الخلايا
that in your brains, exactly now, as you watch me doing this,
أن دماغك، الآن بالضبط، بينما تشاهدوني أفعل هذا،
you are activating exactly the same neurons
فانك تُفعّل بالضبط نفس الخلايا العصبية
as if you do the actions.
كما لو أنك تقوم بنفس الفعل.
It looks like this is the leading edge in terms of rehabilitation.
والأمر يبدو رائداً من ناحية إعادة التأهيل.
But one day we found that Mario
لكن في أحد الأيام أكتشفنا أن ماريو
was not looking at our hand.
لم يكن ينظر لأيادينا.
He was looking at us.
لقد كان ينظر إلينا.
We were his mirror.
لقد كنا نحن المرآة بالنسبة له.
And the problem, as you might feel,
والمشكلة، كما قد تشعرون،
is that we were down, we were depressed,
أننا كنا مُحبطين، و متشائمين،
we were looking at him as a problem,
وكنا ننظر إليه كمشكلة،
not as a son, not from a positive perspective.
وليس كإبن، ليس من وجهة نظر إيجابية.
And that day really changed our perspective.
وذلك اليوم قام بتغيير وجهة نظرنا.
We realized that we had to become
لقد ادركنا بأنه ينبغي علينا أن نكون
a better mirror for Mario.
مرآة أفضل لماريو.
We restarted from our strengths,
لقد بدأنا مجدداً من قوانا،
and at the same time we restarted from his strengths.
وفي نفس الوقت بدأنا من قواه هو.
We stopped looking at him as a problem,
أوقفنا النظر إليه كمشكلة،
and we started to look at him as an opportunity to improve.
وبدأنا بالنظر إليه كفرصة للتحسّن.
And really, this was the change,
وحقاً، كان ذلك تغييراً،
and from our side, we said,
ومن جانبنا، قلنا،
"What are our strengths that we really can bring to Mario?"
"ما هي القوة التي يمكن إعطائها لماريو؟"
And we started from our passions.
وبدأنا من شغفنا.
I mean, at the end, my wife and myself
أعني من جانبي، زوجتي وأنا
are quite different,
مختلفين تماماً،
but we have many things in common.
لكن لدينا أشياء كثير نتشاركها.
We love to travel, we love music,
نحن نحب السفر، نحب الموسيقى،
we love to be in places like this,
ونحب أن نكون في أماكن مثل هذه،
and we started to bring Mario with us
وبدأنا بأخذ ماريو معنا
just to show to him the best things that we can show to him.
لنريه أفضل الأشياء التي يمكننا أن نعرضها عليه.
This short video is from last week.
هذا الفيديو من الأسبوع الماضي.
I am not saying --
أنا لا أقول --
(Applause) —
(تصفيق) --
I am not saying it's a miracle. That's not the message,
أنا لا أقول أنها معجزة. ليست تلك الرسالة،
because we are just at the beginning of the path.
لأننا مازلنا في بداية الطريق.
But we want to share what was the key learning,
لكننا نريد أن نتشارك مفتاح التعلّم،
the key learning that Mario drove to us,
مفتاح التعلّم الذي قادنا اليه ماريو،
and it is to consider what you have as a gift
هو أن تعتبر ما لديك كهبة
and not only what you miss,
وليس فقط ما ينقصك،
and to consider what you miss just as an opportunity.
وأن تعتبر ما ينقصك كفرصة.
And this is the message that we want to share with you.
وهذه هي الرسالة التي أردنا تشاركها معكم.
This is why we are here.
لهذا السبب نحن هنا.
Mario!
ماريو!
And this is why --
ولهذا السبب --
(Applause) —
(تصفيق) --
And this is why
لهذا السبب
we decided to share the best mirror in the world with him.
قررنا أن نتشارك أفضل مرآة في العالم معه.
And we thank you so much, all of you.
ونشكركم جميعاً، كل الشكر.
FF: Thank you. RD: Thank you. Bye.
شكراً لكم شكراً لكم. الى اللقاء.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
FF: Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً لكم. (تصفيق)